Okay, the next example is a really
exciting ending of the finals
of the World Pool Masters versus Darren
Appleton in 2013 in Barnsley, England,
about 20 miles from where Darren lives.
DARREN APPLETON
SO, I PICKED THIS EXAMPLE because I'm
facing a really hostile crowd, not in a
very negative way. They weren't
against me,
but they were really pro Darren.
So, everything that was happening was uh
exaggerated times 10.
And um
it was kind of like playing the Mosconi
in a way.
Um I don't know what I'm doing there
with the yawning, but
I'm about to close out the match, guys.
I'm up 7-6. It was a dog fight. It was a
great match. A lot of uh things were
happening. We both really wanted to win.
Uh and I broke the balls extremely well.
And I'm about to close out this match.
And I'm going to show you another mental
error, but also how I recovered from
that.
So, I'm not showing you all the
hinky-dory great shots and great jumps.
I'm showing you the mental side of
correcting stuff here also.
What's happening here?
I got the 5-7 combination lined up.
And
the reason I make the upcoming mental
error is because
uh a week ago or so or 10 days ago with
this same shot,
I followed the five in after the ball
that was in the pocket. That's why I'm
getting up. I remember this now, like,
"Mhm."
I don't want to follow this ball in. And
I was a little bit afraid if I didn't
roll this combination very
well, the ball was going to end up funky
next to the pocket. So, I'm taking a
chance here to follow that ball in cuz
it's so deep. I'm thinking if I hit it
straight, it's going in.
And there you see,
bad choice of shot. I didn't hit it
straight. All I had to do was roll it in
and then go back upwards.
So, an error. I have no time anymore. I
got a shot clock.
I'm Of course, I'm disgusted with the
choice, but I'm thinking, "Okay, let's
go."
Right? I practiced really hard on my
safety drills in that period. This is an
extremely tough shot. I can only see the
left side of the ball.
But I have to keep going, guys. I cannot
just give it away. I'm up 7-6.
So,
my instincts got
kicked in there and I execute this ball
really well. And from here, at least I'm
I didn't give up. I didn't sell out
after a mistake. I'm still in the I have
the initiative of this rack.
Darren has to make a really good shot
here to recover.
Darren is a great champion. We all know
that. So, he's he's not going to let
this one slip that easy. He's glad to be
at the table. That's his mentality,
right? The match was over.
Whatever he's got to shoot at, just
just give it to me. So, he executes a
beautiful touchy roll safety there.
Which he he took a big chance for the
table to roll off.
Executed well.
Fortunately for me, if I want to play
safe here, the five ball will stay
approximately the same position. So, I
can hit the right side of the five here,
guys. The five will almost not move that
much and I can really try to get the cue
ball two or three rails behind the nine.
If the five would be off a little bit,
would be much tougher. So,
I'm still in the match. I have a chance
again to regain initiative here.
One, two, see the five doesn't move that
much.
I hit it a little bit hard. The
adrenaline's of course kicking in big
time now for the win. And what's also
interesting is
a few weeks before
in the World Cup of Pool
and Nick van den Berg and me, we got a
runner-up against the Philippines.
And we didn't close out the last
uh few games.
That missed eight will haunt Niels for
the rest of his life.
Which was uh painful. And uh actually,
we didn't do that a year after against
uh Darren and Karl, also.
THE BIGGEST nine England has hit IN
THEIR LIVES.
BUT that's also a part of the game,
guys. It comes back to mentality. How
are you going to take that?
Right? I think a positive way to take
those matches is listen, we played great
that tournament. We didn't play great
for maybe one or two games. Right? Does
that mean now that we're bad players? Is
that what we should think about? Only
that? No, man. We played really good.
We're in good form.
We're putting ourselves in positions
where we can win. Take that.
Right? Great shot from Darren there
under pressure.
But take that form and carry it over. If
you keep putting yourself in positions
where you can win, right? Eventually,
you're going to bust through the door.
And that's what we see here. Of course,
in my mind right now, I'm thinking, "Oh,
man.
I've I've given it away again." But But
sticking with it, right? I'm battling my
own little demon there, my gremlin
in my mind, and I'm just hoping for a
chance. This shot's not easy for Darren,
so I'm thinking, you know what?
Get ready for a chance.
Darren had a hard time with the crowd
there also.
I heard afterwards because he made that
great bank, the crowd was cheering for
him, right? And here I have to go
through my own little demon
of closing it out there after I just
lost a tough final against the
Philippines with Nick. So this is my
opportunity to set it straight.
I have three balls to go.
Of course, I'm nervous here like any
other human being would be
for winning a big title.
World Pool Masters, this was my first
World Pool Masters, so uh
I'm feeling it.
I don't know why.
Nice speed control there, a little bit
high. One more shot.
YES!
COME ON!
FANTASTIC FINAL.
AND JUST an example of closing it out
and actually mistake tilt.
We go over that in the course. All
right, celebrations. There you have it,
another example.
Tremendous stuff.